בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is כ"א, Chaf Aleph, and
we pick up with a משנה Mishnah on the bottom of כ'
עמוד ב'. Chaf Amud Bet. And we get into stuff that is
very, very practical,
stuff we can really relate to, issues about zoning and encroaching on
people's business. So let's take a look. The משנה Mishnah at the
bottom of
כ', Chaf, I'm going to read it again, we had it at
the end of yesterday. חנות שבחצר: Chanut she-be-chatzer: if you have a
store in a courtyard. So courtyard has I don't know exactly how
many homes, let's say 10-12 homes, not huge. יכול למחות בידו: Yachol
limchot beyado: so somebody wants to open up a store in the
courtyard. You know it's a residential area. So here we're getting into
zoning issues. So somebody wants to open up a grocer or something
within the courtyard. So somebody can object and say, "אני יכול לישון
מכל הנכנסים ומכל היוצאים. Ani yachol lishan mikol hanechnasim umikol hayotzim. I
can't deal with all the noise of everybody coming, all these outsiders
coming in and out of our courtyard." Now somebody's sort of people
have commented that "I can't sleep" makes it suggest like it's only
a problem based on the fact that it's early hours or late
hours. I didn't get a chance to look it up, but I
imagine that that's not, you don't have to limit it to the
issue of sleeping. The point is, is that I have a right
to not have my courtyard overrun with all of this outside traffic.
So therefore a person is not allowed to do that. אבל, Aval,
עושה כלים, oseh kelim, but you can in your home go ahead
and make vessels. יוצא ומוכר Yotze umocheir and take it out into
the marketplace, ומוכר בתוך השוק. umocheir betoch hashuk. So you can't stop
somebody from making things in their home if they're not bringing in
a lot of outside traffic, even though the making things is going
to be causing noise. ואינו יכול למחות בידו V'eino yachol limchot beyado
and you can't prevent that person and say ולא לומר לו, velo
lomar lo, "אני יכול לישון לא מכל הפטיש ולא מכל הריחיים. Ani
yachol lishan lo mikol hapatish velo mikol harechayim. I can't sleep because
of the hammer or because of the millstone, ולא מכל התינוקות velo
mikol hatinokot or because of the children." Now we're going to discuss
who the children are. If they're children coming in to buy things
that the earlier story about bringing in outsiders, so we'll discuss the
issue of the children in a minute. But the basic difference is
is that you don't have a right, and anybody who's ever lived
in an apartment building knows what this is like, when the neighbor
downstairs or whatever complain about the noise. Right? Or sometimes you're the
one complaining about the noise. How much do you have to do
to not do things in your own domain that are making noise
and disturbing other people? So that you don't have to stop. But
what you can't do is you can't basically open up a commercial
enterprise in the sense that's going to bring in, I mean I
guess you could make stuff that's for the sake of selling, but
you cannot go ahead and make something that's going to bring in
outside traffic. That you're not allowed to do, but apparently making noise
סתם stam is not a problem. You can throw parties late at
night. Now that does raise an interesting question, right, about can you
make noise at all times? Can you go ahead and have your
and be making your stuff at three in the morning? So that
I don't know. All right? But basically within a certain amount of
a tolerable limit, you can go ahead and do stuff certainly in
your own home. It's not the noise per se, it's the noise
of bringing in all of these people from the outside. So let's
take a look like I mean while one wonders, let's say you
bring in a lot of outside traffic and there would be no
noise. Like let's say you would have a silent meditation retreat going
on in your house and nobody was able to say a word,
right, but yet just tons of people coming back and forth. So
it's an interesting distinction, right? People coming in which are making noise,
that you can stop. סתם stam making noise, you're not allowed to
prevent your neighbor. So anyway, let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says, "מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא?"
Mai shna reisha u-mai shna seifa? Now why in the beginning can
you stop people from coming in, opening up a store and bringing
in outside foot traffic, and in the end it says you can't
stop the תינוקות, tinokot, the sound of the children, and the גמרא
Gemara assumes that this means that the children are coming in to
buy stuff from your shop or whatever that you've opened up in
the חצר? chatzer? So why are you not allowed to stop that?
You can, you're allowed to prevent outside foot traffic. So אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, "סיפא אתיין לחצר אחרת." Seifa asyan l'chatzer acheret. No,
no, no. The end what we're saying is is that you've opened
up your store in another חצר. chatzer. So then it's seemingly obvious
you could open up your, so people of the other חצר chatzer
don't mind, the yard nearby. And obviously you can't object, like so
just imagine, all
right, so here's one חצר, chatzer, right,
and this would be the מבוי, mavoi, and then here's the next
חצר, chatzer, right. So if you have a home here,
let's say you got a home here and somebody else over here
decides that he's going to open up a חנות chanut and nobody
in this courtyard mind, you can't go ahead and say, I mean
you could understand why, you can't go ahead and say, "Look, so
many people are coming down the street and going into your courtyard
to buy from your store that even if people in your courtyard
don't mind the noise and they're happy to have the store and
happy to have the business, it's creating a lot of noise that's
carrying over and it's creating a lot of foot traffic in the
street." That you're not allowed to object to. It's not, they're not
going into your courtyard. There's a limit what you can. object to.
So that's what אביי Abaye says. The case that you can't object
to the sound of the kids, which is understood here to mean
that they're going in to buy stuff in the street, is when
the store was opened up in a neighboring courtyard.
Well, it's a hard, yeah, it shouldn't be specifically kids. And it's
actually, the better read is what רבא Rava says, that we're not
talking about buyers at all. We're talking about a different case. So
אמר ליה רבא, Amar Lei Rava, so if רבא Rava said, אי
הכי רישני חצר אחרת מותר, Icha Rishni Chatzer Acheires Mutar, then it's
not about kids, it's about if another courtyard is allowed. אלא אמר
רבא, Ela Amar Rava, so רבא Rava says no, סיפא אתאן לתינוקות
של בית רבן. Seifa Atan Letinokos Shel Beis Rabban. Now, the end
is talking about school children, that you wanted to open up a
schoolyard, a school, you know, in your home. That, even though that
brings in, so that's a חידוש, chidush, you know, talk about things
that make a lot of noise. You open up a school with
all the kids, right? It's going to have all the hustle and
bustle in the morning dropping them off and then bringing at the
end, then at the end of the day, and then during the
day making all that noise. Okay, and that you're not allowed to
object to. So that's very strange. You can object to a store
and you can't object to a school opening up next door? So
why is that? That's because of the primacy that we've always put
on education.
ומהתקנת יהושע בן גמלא, U-Meihiskanas Yehoshua ben Gamla, and the reason you
cannot object to a school opening up next door is because of
the תקנה takanah of רב יהושע בן גמלא Rav Yehoshua ben Gamla
ואילך, ve-eilech, and from that point on. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב,
Di-amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, ברם זכור אותו האיש לטוב, Bram Ha-zachor
Oso Ha-ish Letov, this man should be remembered for good, יהושע בן
גמלא שמו, Yehoshua ben Gamla shemo, שאילמלא הוא, she-imalei hu, was it
not for him,
נשתכח תורה מישראל. nishtakach Torah mi-Yisrael. תורה Torah would have been forgotten
from the Jewish people. שבתחילה, She-batchila, what did he do? He invested
in primary education. Not only that, in public school education. שבתחילה She-batchila
he did, מי שיש לו אב מלמדו תורה, mi she-yeish lo av
melamdo Torah, מי שאין לו אב לא היה לומד תורה. mi she-ein
lo av lo hayah lomeid Torah. Somebody who had a father, the
father who was presumably also able to do it would teach him
תורה, Torah, and somebody who did not have a father or whose
father wasn't able, did not learn תורה. Torah. It was taken as
an individual obligation. Every, you know, every person has the obligation and
some people were able to benefit from and some people got educated
and some didn't. So מי mi לא lo מאי דרש? mai darash?
דרש. darash. What do they teach, what do they learn? ולמדתם אותם.
ve-limadetem osam. ולמדתם אתם. ve-limadetem atem. That
you should go ahead
and sort of learn like, I think this is that he when
explicated that, well, רש״י Rashi learns it, ולמדתם אותם האב עצמו מצווה
ללמדו. ve-limadetem osam ha-av atzmo metzuveh le-lamdo. You teach your children but
not as a collective obligation. So that, I don't, I've always thought
that this מאי דרש mai darash could have been not that like
it's a,
like what did the fathers דרשן? darshan? What did they דרשן darshan
before him? I mean that's what I think it's saying. They דרשנו
darshaned before him that it's a private obligation. You teach your own
kids, it's not a communal one. But anyway, fine. So that's the
way it's being read. התקינו, Hiskinu, so then to respond to that
they established, שיהיו מושיבין מלמדי תינוקות בירושלים, she-yehu moshivin melamdei tinokos bi-Yirushalayim,
that they switched it from a personal obligation and a private obligation
to a communal one and they basically set up schools, you know,
presumably at the public expense in Jerusalem. מאי דרש? mai darash? Now
כי מציון תצא תורה, Ki Mi-Tzion Teitzei Torah,
from Zion תורה Torah will go out. So this מאי דרש mai
darash makes it sound like the מאי דרש mai darash is used
to explicate like why they, you know, were coming to respond to
this sense that it's only a private obligation. Which makes me wonder
even if the earlier מאי דרש mai darash is not what the
originally people were saying, but the response to the idea that it
was a private obligation is don't read it ולמדתם אותם, ve-limadetem osam,
you teach, ולמדתם אתם ve-limadetem atem collectively, that you collectively have a
communal obligation and it's not just each person's father teaches them but
it's אתם atem as a collective has an obligation. Anyway, but certainly
by the second stage they were saying no, we're going to set
up this free system in
Jerusalem. Now כי מציון תצא תורה... Ki Mi-Tzion Teitzei Torah...
Asking that פסוק pasuk why they should set up in Jerusalem? Yeah,
well no that is the פסוק pasuk why they should set up
in Jerusalem. Right. Right.
You should read it that the מאי דרש mai darash applies to
the following stage. So ולמדתם אתם ve-limadetem atem is make it collective,
and כי מציון תצא תורה Ki Mi-Tzion Teitzei Torah is leaving Jerusalem,
it's like going spreading from out further from... Oh, I don't know
because it doesn't work in the like then the next line says
ועדיין. ve-adayin. Then it says like that was what they דרשנו, darshaned,
but then there was still a problem. ועדיין, ve-adayin, so it doesn't
sound like that was what pushed them to the next stage. So
it does sound like the פסוק pasuk is being quoted to like
what justified that stage. So what justified the stage of making it
private was ולמדתם אותם, ve-limadetem osam, teach your own kids. But then
כי מציון תצא תורה Ki Mi-Tzion Teitzei Torah made it sort of
collective and you do it from Jerusalem.
ועדיין, ve-adayin, but that didn't solve the problem. מי שיש לו אב
היה מעלו ומלמדו. mi she-yeish lo av hayah ma-alo u-melamdo. Even if
it was available, it wasn't available equally to everybody. If you had
a father who could, you know, get you to Jerusalem, fine.
מי שאין לו אב לא היה עולה ולומד. mi she-ein lo av
lo hayah oleh ve-lomeid. be able to make it up to ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, even if it was so, it might be available to all,
but it was still selective, it was still not equally accessible to
all. התקינו שיהיו מושיבין בכל פלך ופלך. hitkinu sheyiyu moshivin bechol pelech
uplech.
So they established fine, not just in one central place, in every
major country. What? פלך, pelech, thank you, פלך. pelech. Okay. אז הת
az hat אין דעת בנשים אלא בפלך. ein da’as banashim ela bapalech.
Isn't that the what do you call it, isn't that the thing
used for sewing or something? Same word? What? Don't know what I'm
talking about? No? It's not the same word? Okay. ומכניסין אותו umachnisin
oso what? בי כשתא? bei kishtha?
No it isn't, I don't think so. פלך, pelech, like the thing
for weaving or whatever. Same in the collar. Yeah, right, right, right.
Anyway, okay, I didn't realize it was the same word. Okay, anyway,
ומכניסין אותו umachnisin oso
fine, in every major, and now so that's like every major district
or whatever, it's bigger than a מדינה, medina, it's bigger than a
country, it's like a region that constitutes multiple countries. So still, I
mean, okay, it's still central, not central one place
in the entire country, one place in each region, but it was
still pretty central, but it was still not well spread out.
ומכניסין אותו כבן שש עשרה וכבן שבע עשרה. umachnisin oso keven shesh
esrei u’keven sheva esrei. And they would only do it
like at the more advanced ages. ומי שהיה רבו כועס עליו, umi
shehaya rabo ko’es alav, but of course that was a little late
to start educating people because
then you went your first fifteen sixteen years without education. So then
you were finally brought into school and your teacher would try to
get you to pay attention and to discipline you. So you'd feel
I'm already an adult, who needs this? ומבעיט בו ויצא, umavit bo
v’yetze, he would like reject, rebel against the master and he would
just leave the רבי. rebbe. עד, ad, so they were starting too
late and it was still too inaccessible. עד שבא יהושע בן גמלא
ותיקן שיהיו מושיבין מלמדי תינוקות בכל מדינה ומדינה ובכל עיר ועיר. ad
sheba Yehoshua ben Gamla v’tiken sheyiyu moshivin melamdei tinokos bechol medina umedina
uvechol ir ve’ir. So then he established, number one, you do it
not just in the פלך, pelech, not just in the big regions
but
in the sub states and not only that, but in every town.
ומכניסין אותו כבן שש וכבן שבע. umachnisin oso keven shesh u’keven sheva.
And you get them started at a nice young age, so that
they learn discipline and they learn the sense of how to
submit themselves and sort of devoting themselves to the learning.
אמר, amar, so that was his major accomplishment. Now because of that
accomplishment, and since it was in every town, so where were you
going to put it in the town? Right? I mean I guess
you could put it in a place that was not in any
courtyard in some own space, but presumably the best place to put
them was in the courtyards. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying
is that once that was the establishment that every town had to
have a school, anybody who wanted to open up a school in
their courtyard the other people could not prevent, even though it was
going to cause a lot of noise in the courtyards, right? Which
is, I don't know, to me that's still pretty interesting. Right? I
mean it's one school for a town, there's multiple courtyards for a
town, it would still seem like why should we be the ones
to have it and it's just going to be so disruptive for
everybody here.
So יהושע בן גמלא, Yehoshua ben Gamla, תוספות Tosfos points out, if
you look at תוספות, Tosfos, הוא אותו איש אמר רב יוסף, hu
oso ish amar Rav Yosef, תוספות Tosfos says זכור אותו איש לטוב
ושמו יהושע בן גמלא שאלמלא הוא נשתכחה תורה מישראל שבתחילה, zechur oso
ish l’tov u’shmo Yehoshua ben Gamla she’ilmala hu nishtakcha Torah miYisrael shebitichila,
איילו ליה מרתא בת בייתוס לינאי המלך. ailu lei Marta bas Boethus
l’Yannai HaMelech. So this was the period of ינאי Yannai which was
the חשמונאים Chashmonaim period. About the second century before the Common Era.
Yeah, so it's making it pretty early. Right,
130... exactly. So it's pretty early. Now that's also relevant, that's also
relevant for the idea that he would make it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
There's a very interesting תוספות Tosfos here which is relevant to all
the people who send their kids to Israel for a gap year.
Look at תוספות Tosfos כי מציון תצא תורה. ki miTzion teitzei Torah.
Seriously, look at this תוספות. Tosfos. He says, לפי שהיה רואה קדושה
גדולה וכהנים עוסקים בעבודה. lefi shehaya ro’eh kedusha gedola v’Kohanim oskim ba’avoda.
So there you go, there's a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash in ירושלים
Yerushalayim and everybody who lives in ירושלים Yerushalayim is very involved in
all these religious pursuits. היה מכוון לבו יותר ליראת שמים. haya mechaven
libo yoser l’yiras Shamayim. So you send, you have the school in
ירושלים Yerushalayim and the kid sees everybody is engaged in religious pursuits
and that makes him more devoted to a type of a religious
life. So it's not just what goes on in the four walls
of the school and how good the education is, it's what the
entire surrounding environment is and what sort of values that is communicating
to the kids. What? Immersive. Immersive, right. And but it's also exactly,
but it's also the culture that's sort of supporting it exactly. ליראת
שמים וללמוד תורה כדתנינן בספרי למען תלמד ליראה. l’yiras Shamayim v’lilmod Torah
k’da’ashinan beSifrei lema’an tilmad leyira. גדול מעשר שני שמביא לידי תלמוד לפי
שהיה עומד בירושלים עד שיאכל מעשר שני שלו. gadol ma’aser sheni shemeivi
lidei talmud lefi shehaya omed b’Yerushalayim ad sheyochal ma’aser sheni shelo. The
whole idea of bringing מעשר שני ma’aser sheni to ירושלים Yerushalayim was
it put you in this entire immersive religious context. והיה רואה שכולם
עוסקים במלאכת שמים ובעבודה היה גם הוא מכוון ליראת שמים ועוסק בתורה.
vehaya ro’eh shekulam oskim b’meleches Shamayim uba’avoda haya gam hu mechaven l’yiras
Shamayim v’osek baTorah. So right, so it's really true. It's like you
go to school in the States and you step right outside and
you're exposed to all of American culture, it's hard to... sustain that
sense of devotion and focus and commitment as if as opposed to
when you step outside and everything supports that type of a life.
So
it's a very powerful point here about this. About education also because
there's no way that I mean this is all foreseeable that the
initial model is not going to be sufficient. Right. What are you
going to take the whole country's children and bring them all to
one... how big was that school going to be? Well, there were
many multiple schools in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Right, but they're going to bring
them to... right, that's a good point too. Like how much initially
was there really a commitment to universal education? Right. How much even
at the earlier stages was there sort of a sense like okay
we're going to make it more available but only for the people
that are really committed? Only for the people, right, as opposed to
this real idea that no you have to educate everyone. You'd say
that he would wise up to establish this kind of stepping stone,
gradual approach to adopting the idea of universal education. Right.
You mean the earlier stages? Right. I mean you have to know
that this is the way it's going to play out. Right, right,
right. But it sounds like he only came in at the final
stage. Those earlier stages were others. But you're right, like at the
earlier stages were they really committed to the idea of universal education
or they were just trying to improve things but still it was
a sense that it was for the elite? Right. Or at least
for those that really were prepared to sacrifice to make it happen.
Yes. They had bed and board for these kids then also, right?
If you're doing it in ירושלים Yerushalayim and in these central locations,
right. Okay, so now so okay so now the גמרא Gemara says
but now we have because of this תקנה takana that every town
so that means that you cannot object to anybody opening up the
school anywhere, which is pretty interesting. אמר ליה רב לרב שמואל בר
שילת, Amar lei Rav l'Rav Shmuel bar Shilat, עד שית, Ad shit,
so we say six or seven by the way, so six or
seven תוספות Tosafot says it depends like if the kid is healthy
or like able to be away from the family at a young
age then six, if it's not
so
ready then
seven. You can see why it's six or seven. Exactly. One or
like which one. Okay, so then he says and what about the
fact that in פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot it says about בן חמש
שנים למקרא? ben chamesh shanim lamikra? So he says that's one that's
like really ready to leave earlier than at an earlier stage. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה רב לרב שמואל בר שילת,
Amar lei Rav l'Rav Shmuel bar Shilat, עד שית לא תקבל, Ad
shit lo tekabel, younger than six don't accept any students, they're too
young. מכאן ואילך קביל, Mikan va'eilach kabeil, from that point on you
should accept ואסקי להו כתורא v'askei lehu ketora and feed them like
a ox, because basically the way you do with an ox is
on the one hand you would sort of like force-feed, you'd actually
like put the food in its mouth. But also one of the
מפרשים mefarshim point out as opposed to a camel where when you
you also sort of there's a word for that for force-feeding an
animal there's a verb, I don't know what it is, what is
it? Anyway, but for a camel you would force-feed but you would
really like do it with like vigor like you would like stuff
it, whereas by an ox it would be more more gentle. So
actually one of the מפרשים mefarshim explain like you know you gotta
stuff them with information, like really just fill them up with as
much תורה Torah and with as much knowledge as
possible but בנחת. b'nachat. Okay, so like that's interesting imagery of ספי
ליה כתורא. safei lei ketora. Is that
a wordplay there? What? Is that a wordplay? תורה Torah with a
like with a hey? That could be, you're right. It did not
occur to me but it very much could
be. Okay, so but just like keep them... it's true like there
are these some schools, my nephews in Israel went to a school
where from a very young age, five or six or whatever, they
just have them like memorize everything. Memorize all of תנ"ך, Tanach, memorize
all of משנה. Mishna. You know you get them at this at
this tender age and you can really just like stuff them with
information. So do it gently but stuff them with as much information
as possible. Any sense here that this is just boys or boys
and girls?
You're right, it's not explicit. I assume in this ברייתא braita it's
boys just because of the cultural reality. But oh
but that was an important question to ask. Also the imagery of
ספי ליה כתורא safei lei ketora is not about like developing the
analytical ability, right? Like it's like at a young age just there
was always an issue in the גמרא, Gemara, like is it more
important the person who has all of this knowledge or the person
who has good analysis and doesn't have as broad base of knowledge?
So at a young age though the idea is just have them
suck up as much knowledge, as much information as possible. The analysis
will come later. ספי ליה כתורא. Safei lei ketora. ואסקי ליה כתורא.
V'askei lei ketora. אמר ליה רב לרב שמואל בר שילת, Amar lei
Rav l'Rav Shmuel bar Shilat, and Rav said to Rav Shmuel bar
Shilat, כי מחית לינוקא, Ki machit l'yanuka, now when you have to
hit the kids, okay, this was before this was when that was
still
acceptable. When you have to hit the kids because they're misbehaving, לא
תמחי אלא בערקתא דמסנא, Lo timchei ela b'arketa d'mesana, only hit them
with a shoelace, meaning not with like that the ruler or the
strap, meaning if you have to give them a פאטש, patch, give
them a פאטש, patch, but don't do it with any real with
like to really hurt them. דקרי קרי, Dekari kari, now דקרי קרי,
Dekari kari, those that know that learn how to read, are able
to read, they'll read. דלא קרי, Delo kari, let's say you got
a kid that's not succeeding and he's not he's not able to
read, so don't kick him out of school. הוותיה לחבריה, Havsei l'chavrei,
let him just sit next to, you know, be pals with the
kid sitting next to him, and so he can't read yet, fine,
there's no reason to kick him out. Now רש״י Rashi says add
to this, eventually he'll learn to read. רש״י Rashi says אין חזקוק
וייסרו יותר מדי, Ein chazakuk veyasro yoter midai,
you know, if a kid isn't learning, maybe it's not the kid's
fault, you know, you or well רש״י Rashi doesn't say that, that's
me saying it. He's maybe he's not ready. You know you don't
have to feel like oh my god, you know, gotta be stricter.
No, you should not be over-disciplinary. ולא לסלקו מלפניך, Velo lesalko mipanecha,
and
don't feel you have to now get you know kick him out
of school. אלא ישב עם אחרים בצוותא, Ela yeshev im acherim betzavsa,
let him sit with others be part of, you know, soak up
from the environment. וסופו לתת לב, Vesofo latet lev, eventually
he'll be able you know he'll focus, he'll learn from his friends.
That's a very nicer like you know balance here between like you
know really taking the job very seriously and on the other hand
like with a certain amount of gentleness.
Okay, מיתיבי Meitivi asks on this. אחד מבני חצר שביקש לעשות רופא
אומן וגרדי ומלמד תינוקות. Echad mivnei chatzer shebikesh la'asot rofe uman vegardi
umelamed tinokot.
Somebody from the courtyard want, now this claim that anybody can open
up a school. We have the following ברייתא. Baraita. Somebody from the
courtyard wants to be a רופא. rofe. Now, I would assume that
means doctor. רש״י Rashi interestingly says רופא rofe means a מוהל, mohel,
which is interesting. Why did רש״י Rashi say it means a doctor?
I don't know.
אומן Uman is a bloodletter, so maybe because the אומן, uman, the
bloodletter was the doctor, so the רופא rofe had to mean something
else. I don't know.
Now גרדי gardi is a what's a גרדי? gardi? It's like a
shoemaker, right? What's a a weaver? I'm sorry, that's right, it's a
weaver, a weaver. ומלמד תינוקות, Umelamed tinokot, and a schoolteacher, so you
want to do any of those things, בני חצר מעכבין עליו, bnei
chatzer me'akvin alav, they can stop you because again, this is going
to be something that's going to bring a lot of search traffic
into the place. Says the גמרא, Gemara, so you see you cannot
open up a school in the courtyard unless everybody's okay with it.
So the גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bamai askinan, what
are we talking about? בתינוקות דעכו״ם. betinokot de'akum. Oh, you're opening up
a school for non-Jews, okay? So that, that you're not allowed to
do. A Jew, you know, a Jewish school, that anybody has a
right to open that up because of this תקנה. takanah. A non-Jewish
school, that's do it somewhere else. Okay, what what what is that?
What is that? There were no schools for non-Jews? What do you
mean what is that? That that there was a Jew who was
מלמד תינוקות. melamed tinokot. Who says he was teaching Torah? Why can't
he be teaching? I don't know. Is that lib about it? Okay,
did it actually happen or is the גמרא Gemara making it up?
Like I don't know. Okay, but it's not saying he's teaching Torah.
You know whatever he's teaching, let's say you just want to open
up a you know a nursery school. It's a good פרנסה, parnasah,
you know. It's not necessarily because you're teaching Torah. I was just
wondering what the reality was. What a non-Jewish court? Oh, we're going
to get to that in a minute about having the non-Jew be
the one who's doing the school. But now we're just talking for
non-Jewish children. But yeah, we're going to get to that in a
minute. But okay, but anyway, but just because the גמרא Gemara says
this as a way of getting out of the ברייתא baraita does
not mean it was a historical reality. Okay.
But we're going to get to that. We're going to get to
that. Okay, but right now, once you don't have the overriding idea,
you know allowance of opening a Jewish school, then you can't open
any business in a courtyard that's going to bring in traffic. תא
שמע, Ta shema, come in here. שנים שיושבים בחצר וביקש אחד מהם
לעשות רופא. Shnayim sheyoshvim bechatzer uvikesh echad mehem la'asot rofe. Again, I
don't know why it describes it in this more personal way as
the you know, but it's the same point as the previous ברייתא.
baraita. Two people are sitting around in a courtyard and one of
them says hey, I think I want to be a doctor or
whatever a מוהל. mohel. ואומן, Ve'uman, or a bloodletter, וגרדי, vegardi, or
a weaver. ומלמד תינוקות, Umelamed tinokot, or a schoolteacher. חברו מעכב עליו.
chavero me'akev alav. The friend says
no you can't, not in this courtyard you can't. So הכא נמי,
hacha nami, so you see same problem. Look הכא נמי בתינוקות דעכו״ם,
hacha nami betinokot de'akum, it means he wanted to be a schoolteacher
for non-Jewish children. תא שמע. Ta shema. מי שיש לו בית בחצר
השותפין, Mi sheyesh lo bayit bechatzer hashutfin, so you have a house
in a joint courtyard, הרי זה לא ישכירנו. harei zeh lo yaskirenu.
So maybe that's the חידוש chiddush also by the way of making
it about two people, that it doesn't matter if it's a courtyard
that has ten houses or that has two houses. But I don't
know why that's a bigger חידוש, chiddush, but okay. I mean one
also wonders, let's say it is a courtyard that has ten houses
and nine of the people are okay with you opening it and
one person is not okay. Like does any one person have a
veto vote? It sounds like that, right? It sounds like that yes,
that fundamentally you don't have a right. If you get everybody to
sign on, fine. But fundamentally anybody can say no, you don't have
a right. Okay, so מי שיש לו בית בחצר
השותפין, mi sheyesh lo bayit bechatzer hashutfin, somebody has a house, הרי
זה לא ישכירנו לא לרופא. harei zeh lo yaskirenu lo lerofe. You
can't, in the same way you can't open up one of these
businesses, you can't rent it to somebody who is opening a business
like this. I mean maybe that's even a bigger חידוש, chiddush, somebody's
an outsider has even less rights in the courtyard.
לא ישכירנו לא לרופא ולא לאומן. Lo yaskirenu lo lerofe velo le'uman.
now the word סופר sofer could mean scribe, so we're going to
but we're going to assume at least the גמרא Gemara initially assumes
it means somehow a schoolteacher. And we're going to assume it means
that it's a schoolteacher or, you know, a Jewish or a non-Jew,
so it's presumably the Jewish schoolteacher means for Jewish children. So the
גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, what are you
talking about בסופר מתא? b'sofer masa? Now what is סופר מתא? sofer
masa? So רש״י Rashi says it means a school, like it's like
not only a one-room schoolhouse, but it's basically, you know, your, it's
like a multi-grade schoolhouse. And therefore that, you're not allowed, even with
this תקנה takkanah that you can have, you need to have schools
in every town, doesn't mean that in a courtyard you can set
up a multi-grade schoolhouse. That, you know, maybe one, one grade per
courtyard or something of that nature. That's how רש״י Rashi explains it.
תוספות, Tosfos, there's another רש״י Rashi in a different גמרא Gemara that
actually has the word not סופר sofer but ספר sapar and has
to say that you're a barber, not a schoolteacher. But תוספות Tosfos
has the best, probably, read, which is that you're a scribe. Who
said that you were a schoolteacher? So if you look at תוספות,
Tosfos, תוספות Tosfos says ולא לסופר ארמאי, v'lo l'sofer Aramai, no, the
other תוספות, Tosfos, בסופר מתא, B'sofer Masa, תוספות Tosfos at the end
says
אלא נראה, Ella ne'ereh, right before the תוספות מתקנת, Tosfos mi-takkanas, אלא
נראה Ella ne'ereh says תוספות, Tosfos, כמו שפירש רב, Kemo she-pirash Rav,
סופר מתא כותב שטרות העיר. sofer masa koseiv shtaros ha-ir. You're basically
the scribe. You write the documents for the city. So then you
don't have a special allowance, you're bringing in outside
traffic, okay. So then we'll get to the later גמרא. Gemara. Now,
by the way, the issue that people were talking about, about issues
of danger in terms of non-Jews in the courtyard, and you know,
that was a
concern particularly in תנאי Tannaic period, the Romans or whatever, you know,
they had a very, they sort of saw them as a real
threat to their safety.
So if you look at תוספות ולא לסופר ארמאי, Tosfos v'lo l'sofer
Aramai, the earlier תוספות, Tosfos, second wide line, he says משמע דאם
לא היה סופר הוה שרי להשכיר לארמאי. mashma d'im lo haya sofer,
hava shari l'haskir l'armai. That you could rent a house in a
courtyard to a non-Jew if it weren't for the problem about the
zoning issue, about bringing in the foot traffic. ואם תאמר דאמרינן בבבא
בתרא, V'im tomar d'amrinan b'Bava Basra, האי בר ישראל דזבין ליה לארמאי
hai bar Yisrael d'zavin lei l'armai לעכום l'akum במצר דבר ישראל חבריה,
b'metzar d'bar Yisrael chavrei, משמתינן ליה, m'shamtanan lei, דאמר ליה ארי ארביעת
לי אמצראי, d'amar lei aryei arveisa ammetzarai,
that somebody who sells a yard,
you know, a neighboring house to a non-Jew, the other person could
say you're bringing this lion
into
the yard because, you know, they were seen as a threat to
safety, to the safety of the Jews. So how come here it's
not a problem? So first תוספות Tosfos says דוחק לחלק בין
מכירה לשכירה. it's dochek l'chaleik bein mechira l'skhira. Well, maybe there's a
difference, selling a house and renting a house. But תוספות Tosfos says
well, if you're really so afraid of your safety, it doesn't make
so much sense that you would make that distinction. So why is
this only not a problem? ונראה לי מדעתם כשישראל רוצה לקנות, V'nirli
mi-da'atan k'she-Yisrael rotzeh liknos, אבל אין ישראל רוצה לקנות מותר. aval ein
Yisrael rotzeh liknos mutar. So, and תוספות, Tosfos, this is a better
distinction. He says it's really not such a huge threat to safety.
It's really that if you had a, it's sort of like the
דינא דבר מצרא dina d'bar metzra which we're going to see, right,
a first refusal. So the point is, why were you selling it
to the non-Jew if there was a Jew who wanted to buy?
Now of course, to our American ears, right, this seems so
deeply offensive, right, the whole issue, what would they call it? Covenant?
No, not pollicing, but when you couldn't, what, the whole idea preventing
blacks from moving into neighborhoods? Restrictive? I know, but I was looking
for the, there's a word for that. It was called, redlining? Yes,
restrictive housing, whatever it was. Anyway, but you know, everyone, I don't
know if you've ever spoken to people in Israel about this. They
are like, they can't believe that Americans have this idea that you
can't control who moves into your community. They have a much more
of this, you know, less of this sort of individual right sense
and more of this communal sense. So, and we want a דתי
Dati community, we should be able to have a דתי Dati community.
If we want a mixed community, we should be able to have
a mixed community. You know, so, and in
Israel there's no problem with these types of laws. Yes. Everywhere? What
do you mean? Like, whatever, you're in a ישוב, yishuv, or התנחלות,
hitnachalut, or קיבוץ kibbutz or something, and there's like a board. Right,
and they totally can control who can move in. Just like the
board can control here. Not housing. Not who moves into a house.
Unless it's an apartment, right, so the board, but no, if a
board of a co-op excluded somebody based on race or religion, they
would, that's completely illegal. Unless they don't do it based solely on
race, they'll exclude you based on a number of other factors. People
get around the law in America, yes. But in Israel, it's not,
you could, wait, I just want to ask. If you're in a
ישוב, yishuv, you could say you're not דתי, Dati, we're not accepting
you. You don't have to find another reason. Okay, so if the
ישוב yishuv is a ישוב דתי. yishuv Dati. Right. Yes, but in
Haifa, Tel Aviv, any neighborhood... I understand. And that's what I'm saying
is, so that's why I give this call. Right, but the point
is things that would never be conceivable in America, that you could
actually
say we're not accepting you because you're not religious, right, that would
never be conceivable in America. And in Israel there's a sense that
we can define, I'm not criticizing, I'm describing you, so anyway we're
going to move on. Okay.
Restricted, yeah, also this was before the rights of the Jews, that
we were actually the ones that were restricted in the past. Exactly,
you know, so I'm just saying this sounds harsh to American ears,
but other places this is like, no, you can control who lives
in your community. Okay, we're going to go on.
Don't take everything so personally. I'm not, I'm not complaining, it's just
the reality. But let's say a group of דתי dati people live
in a community and someone decides I'm not דתי dati anymore, would
they be able to throw them out? That I don't know, you
have to ask. I wonder if you could have a דוקא חילוני
davka chiloni community in Israel that wouldn't accept דתיים. dati'im. What do
you think, is that possible? You can't do that, you can't... Fine,
whatever, okay, fine, all right.
Fine.
I'll ask my sister. But you can invite some black people and
ask them if they think America really allows everybody to live everywhere.
All right, I'm not... moving on.
Moving on. All right, גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says where were we?
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: תא שמע... Ta shma...
where was I? Okay,
הני דאמר, Hani d'amar, right, after יהושע בן גמלא. Yehoshua ben Gamla.
Oh, fine. הא רמינן ביהושע בן גמלא. Ha ramminan b'Yehoshua ben Gamla.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, מתקנת יהושע בן גמלא ואילך לא ממטינן לינוקא
ממתא למתא. mitakanat Yehoshua ben Gamla v'eilach lo mamtinan l'yanuka mimata l'mata.
So from that point on, since we have to have a school
in every town, you cannot bring a... you cannot say, you know,
we're not going to have a school in this town and let
the kids come from
the neighboring town. No, every town... no busing... every town has to
have its own school. אבל מבי כנישתא לבי כנישתא ממטינן. Aval mibei
knishta l'bei knishta mamtinan. But you don't have to have it in
every like neighborhood in every town. You can make them go... so
this is interesting because this makes it sound like the schools would
actually be in the בית כנסת. beit knesset. So you can
actually... so you can say we're not going to have it in
this בית כנסת, beit knesset, you know, we're going to have it
in another one and everybody will come from like the neighboring ones
as long as it's within the same town. ואי מפסיק נהרא, V'ei
mafsik nahara, however, if there's a river to get from like one
neighborhood to the next, then לא ממטינן, lo mamtinan, you can't force
them to go across the river because then that's a danger. ואי
איכא תיתורא, V'ei ika titura, if there's however a stable bridge, ממטינן,
mamtinan, then you can. ואי איכא גמלא, V'ei ika gamla, however, if
there's not a big stable bridge but more like a footbridge which
is more, you know, the way רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom describes it
is that there's ropes on either side and you know you need
to be like big and to hold on to the ropes, so
that's obviously pretty dangerous, so לא ממטינן, lo mamtinan, then you cannot
and then you have to make one
on their side. That's a
גמלא. gamla. ובר גמלא? U'var gamla? יהושע בן גמלא. Yehoshua ben Gamla.
That's a good point. Okay, ואמר רבא. V'amar Rava. Now here becomes
a very interesting line which is, which is two radically different interpretations
of the ראשונים. Rishonim. You'll be able to find the logical gap
between these statements. סך מקרי דרדקי עשרין וחמשה ינוקי. Sach mikrei dardeki
esrin v'chamsha yanukei. The number of children per teacher is 25. ואי
איכא חמשים, V'ei ika chamshin,
now if there are 50, מותבינן תרי, motvinan trei, then you have
two teachers, all right. ואי איכא ארבעין, V'ei ika arbayin, now once
there are... if there are 40 kids, מוקמינן ריש דוכנא, mokeiman reish
duchna, then you have like an assistant teacher. Now, what is the
problem with that? 25 kids to a teacher, 50 kids you have
two teachers, 40 kids you have an assistant teacher. 39 kids... forget
39, 26. What do you mean 25 kids per teacher? What about
26 kids? Then you should already need an assistant. So how do
you read it... what do you do between 25 and 40? Right?
So there are two very different reads.
רמב"ם Rambam and
like a lot of the ראשוני ספרד Rishonei Sfarad read it the
following way: they read up to 25 is one teacher. Any more
than 25 is an assistant, okay? Up to 40. So when they
say 40 is an assistant, that means up to 40 you can
be satisfied with an assistant. From 40 on you can't be satisfied
with an assistant, you need a second teacher until 50. And then
once you get to 50, then two teachers aren't going to be
enough, you're going to need to bring in another assistant. Okay, so
that basically means the maximum class size with one single teacher is
25, more than that you need an assistant.
תוספות Tosafot reads it differently.
Two classes, right. That way when you get to 50, then you
can't have more than 50 kids even with more than two teachers.
Right, because then you're going to need an assistant because it's right...
but even if you had more classes, more than 50 in a
class is too much no matter how much staff you have. Oh,
you mean you would need to break it up. Yeah, that's a
good point. When it says
מותבינן תרי motvinan trei does... The ראשוני אשכנז Rishonei Ashkenaz and one
wonders if this actually reflects differences in not only in reading but
in the societies that that in they read it the following way,
which is probably a better read of the גמרא, Gemara, this second
reading, which is they say, oh, fewer than twenty-five you can't force
somebody to make a school in the town. Fewer than twenty-five, if
the town only has ten kids, then you can't bus them to
the next town. So because right before we had this הלכה halacha
about bussing them to the next town. So fewer than twenty-five you
can't bus them to the next town. By twenty-five you need to
make a school in your town. But you can have one teacher
for anywhere from twenty-five to forty. It's only once you hit forty
that you need an assistant teacher. And then once you hit fifty
then you need to have two teachers. So they actually read that
you can have a class size as big as forty, which is
much, much larger in terms of the class size. So yes. It's
thirty-two. Thirty-two. So somewhere between that's the פשרה pshara between the twenty-five
and the forty. Okay, fine. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, ואמר רבא V'amar Rava said, היי מקרי
ינוקי דגריס והאי אחרינא דגריס טפי. hai makrei yenukei degaris vehai achrina
degaris tfei.
Now, let's say you have a teacher that knows, that learns, but
there's another teacher that learns better. Now, it's interesting, they're talking about
learning, not teaching, okay, which is very fascinating. And obviously you have
to be learned in order to know in order to teach, but
as we know, though sometimes, you know, people can know a lot
and not teach well and vice versa. Anyway, you have the current
teacher, but there's another one who learns better. לא מסלקינן ליה, Lo
mesalkinan lei, you don't fire the existing teacher to hire the other
one, דלמא אתי לידי פשיעותא dilma atei lidei peshiuta because maybe the
second teacher will figure, ha, they fired the other one for me,
I'm the world's best teacher and therefore he doesn't have to do
a good enough job. Of course, רב דימי Rav Dimi says the
obvious response to this. So רב דימי מנהרדעא Rav Dimi miNehardea אמר,
amar, no, כל שכן דגריס טפי. kol sheken degaris tfei. If people
know that their job isn't secure because they can get fired because
another better person is coming around, so the guy that took over,
you know, שמעון Shimon who took over ראובן's Reuven job, now שמעון
Shimon is going to be on his toes because he knows the
next guy who turns the corner could be better than him. קנאת
סופרים תרבה חכמה, Kinat soferim tarbe chochma, right, the jealousy amongst the
scribes. Scribes obviously is teacher, you know, it keeps everybody not just
because you don't want you know you want to be smarter than
the next person but now also because you want to be make
sure you keep your job and the next guy who proves better
than you won't take your job from you. ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava,
and רבא Rava said, הני תרי מקרי דרדקי חד גריס וחד לא
דייק וחד דייק ולא גריס. hanei try makrei dardekei chad garis vechad
lo dayek vechad dayek velo garis. So here it gets the difference
between teaching ability and knowledge. Two school
teachers. One is very knowledgeable, but he's not so careful in how
he teaches the kids. Okay.
And now רש״י Rashi says it means that it's not that he
doesn't do a good job in the initial teaching but he's not
like on top of them to make sure they do their lessons
and that they don't forget. וחד דייק ולא גריס, V'chad dayek velo
garis, the other one is very attentive, but he is not as
knowledgeable. So which one is the better teacher? מסבינן ההוא דגריס ולא
דייק. Masvinan hahu degaris velo dayek. So the first opinion, רבא Rava
is, you have the one who knows more and even if he's
less attentive. שבשתא ממילא נפק, Shabeshta mimeila nafak,
mistakes will go away by themselves. Okay. So they'll learn from the,
they'll get all this knowledge and if they are not good in
their doing their lessons or whatever, you know, they'll still absorb more
from this person. Okay. So it doesn't mean that this person teaches
incorrect information. He teaches correct information, but he's not on top of
them to make sure they're doing their homework and stuff. So that'll
solve itself. Okay.
I know, wait, we have to hear the opposing opinion. רב דימי
מנהרדעא Rav Dimi miNehardea אמר, amar, מסבינן דדייק ולא גריס. masvinan dedayek
velo garis.
No, no, no. Better to have somebody who's on top of the
kids even if he's not as knowledgeable. שבשתא כיון דעל על. Shabeshta
kivan d'al al. Once a mistake goes in, it stays in. So
it's actually it's much more important that the initial knowledge that they
get is accurate even if it's less than getting more that's inaccurate.
Yes. Why in the language are you understanding this statement to be
between the teacher who knows more and the teacher who knows less,
as opposed to both teachers are command the material, one covers
more material but not carefully, and the other one covers goes slower,
they learn less material but more carefully?
I mean רש״י Rashi says דגריס ולא דייק, degaris velo dayek, רש״י
Rashi says שלומד הרבה shelomed harbe not שמלמד הרבה. shemelamed harbe.
גריס Garis normally means how much you're learning not how much you're
teaching.
I think רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says the same thing. He says
where'd he say?
Anyway, I think he says the same thing. I think he says
that the word גורס... gores... The very last part I think,
גורס, Gores, the last line. You know what he says? והכי צריך
למיכנא דאידך מאיים שלא יעבור אחריו דגרס טפי מיניה ומדסקינן בהדיא משום
קנאת סופרים דהא מרחא גריס הרבה ולא דייק כולי האי. Vehachi tzarich
le-michna de-idach me'ayem shelo ya'avor acharyo degaris tefei mineih umidaskinan behadya mishum
kinat sofrim de-ha morcha garis harbe velo dayek kuli hai. No, that’s
not the
part. Anyway fine.
But anyway but רש״י Rashi always says the standard word גרסת Garsat
means to learn, not to teach.
I don’t know, maybe somebody translates it otherwise. רש״י Rashi
I thought meant to read. Yeah, so you’re learning, you’re reading, not
you’re teaching.
How do they translate it there in English?
Teaching?
Really?
Because רש״י Rashi has לומד. Lomed. For רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel he
teaches it at a faster pace. Yeah, yeah, that's the way I
always understood it. Like you’ve got two teachers, both competent. One covers
a lot of ground but he’s not concerned not careful with the
way he’s not careful with the
in terms of like whether they make mistakes or
whatever because... No I hear that, I hear that. I’m just
saying I was being led by רש״י, Rashi, but okay, I hear
the reading. Okay.
Never thought that you know the difference between צול Tzol and צל
Tzal and these types of things is not such a... You think
לומד Lomed means can be מלמד Melamed in this context? That’s the
way I... Okay. They learn together, right? Like even here in ישיבה
Yeshiva we could say oh let’s learn, it means teaching. It makes
a big difference. If you understand it that way it makes a
big difference. In other words, it’s like you have you see those
teachers. Yeah, yeah. So then you’re right. No, that’s more helpful. That’s
more helpful to understand the difference. One who’s sort of just dumping
a lot of information. And you could say if you’re dumping a
lot of information, even if they cover a lot of ground, even
if they only get 80% of it, so then they’ll still get
a lot. And the other one is doing less information, teaching less,
and he’s actually being more careful that what they get they get
properly. He’s making the point that you make a strong case like
if you never teach something that has to be
untaught later type thing. Right, right. Alright. Alright. So okay. So I
appreciate that. You see what my problem was was that I learned
it incorrectly when I was young so I forgot. So alright.
What does the note say? From רש״י? Rashi? תוספות Tosafot says it’s
not that the teacher himself reads it inaccurately. No, that he’s not
on top of the kids, right. Like that I know. The דייק
Dayek is clearly the question about whether he’s on top of them
not whether he’s being inaccurate. The question was whether the גורס Garas
meant how much he knows or how much he teaches. But I
appreciate it’s making a stronger, a clearer point of a clearer difference
if we’re to contrast somebody who teaches a lot of information but
he’s not careful that they do the work as opposed to on
top of them as opposed to teaching less but more on top
of them. Okay. So now it comes once more a degree of
firing the teacher who’s not as good. You want to motivate the
fired teacher to improve.
Right, that was רש״י Rashi read it that way, yeah, that’s true.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. דכתיב. De-chtiv. Now
we’re going to have an example about how important it is to
be on top of people that they learn correctly. כי ששת חדשים
ישב שם יואב וכל ישראל עד הכרית כל זכר באדום. Ki sheishet
chodashim yashav sham Yoav ve-chol Yisrael ad hichrit kol zachar be-Edom. I
just said it correctly. Okay,
so this is actually relating to this week’s פרשה Parsha about עמלק.
Amalek. Okay, they stayed there until they killed off all of the
males. כי אתא לקמיה דדוד, Ki ata lekamei de-Dovid, so דוד Dovid
said to him, אמר ליה, Amar lei, מאי טעמא עבדת הכי? Mai
ta'ama avadat hachi? Why did you this is also why did you
do this that you only killed the males and not the females?
אמר ליה דכתיב תמחה את זכר עמלק. Amar lei de-chtiv timche et
zachar Amalek. He read it זכר Zachar not זכר Zecher עמלק. Amalek.
Okay. So אמר ליה והנן זכר קרינן. Amar lei vehanan Zecher karinan.
But that's not the way you read the פסוק. Pasuk. The פסוק
Pasuk is the memory of, so you have to wipe them all
out. אמר ליה אנא זכר אקריון. Amar lei ana Zachar akreyun. No,
no, when I was a kid they always read the פסוק Pasuk
to me זכר, Zachar, not זכר. Zecher. So אזל שייליה לרביה. Azal
shaylei lerabeih.
They asked the רבי. Rebbe. אמר ליה היכי אקריתן? Amar lei heichi
akreitan? How did you have him read it? אמר ליה... Amar lei...
now here the question is unfortunately the גמרא Gemara doesn't have נקודות.
nekudot. So we'd be inclined to say אמר ליה זכר Amar lei
Zachar because that’s he taught him incorrectly. But תוספות Tosafot says no,
because then the teacher made the mistake. That’s not the point of
the גמרא. Gemara. The point is he said the right thing. אמר
ליה זכר. Amar lei Zecher. I taught him the right thing. So
you said you read the פסוק Pasuk correctly in class. The only
problem was you didn’t follow up with the kid to make sure
he heard it correctly. That’s a much more sharper read, right? I
taught it correctly but he heard it incorrectly and it was the
teacher's fault that the teacher wasn't making sure that the kid actually
got it right. Okay, so that’s the way תוספות Tosafot reads it.
So שקל סייפא, Shakal saifa, so דוד Dovid took a sword, למקטליה,
le-miktaleih, he wanted to kill the teacher because he did this terrible
thing. אמר ליה אמאי? Amar lei amai? Why? אמר ליה דכתיב ארור
עושה מלאכת ה' רמיה. Amar lei de-chtiv arur oseh melechet Hashem remiyah.
Cursed is the one that does God’s turns God’s labor like deceitful.
Like
you weren’t you know you didn't you didn’t have the right work
ethic when it came to מלאכת שמים. melechet Shamayim. You know, you
cut corners. So אמר ליה שבקיה לההוא גברא דליקם בארור. Amar lei
shevakeih le-hahu gavra delikam bearur. Okay, let me get the ארור, Arur,
you don’t have to kill me. ואמר ליה דכתיב... Ve-amar lei de-chtiv...
ואמר ליה כתיב וארור מנע חרבו מדם. va'amar lei ksiv v'arur mone'a
charvo mi'dam. The end of the פסוק pasuk says, cursed is the
one who does not let the who holds back his sword from
blood. I've got to act on this, you deserve to be killed.
So איכא דאמרי קטליה, ika d'amri katlei, some say he killed him
in the end. איכא דאמרי לא קטליה, ika d'amri lo katlei, he
didn't. And that's the end of that story. Okay, but it suggests
it's Yoav, not David.
Oh, Yoav is the one. Oh, I see. Yoav is now the
one, maybe because Yoav is the more violent one, I don't know.
Or because he was a teacher, I don't know. What? Maybe because
it says so, it says Yoav, but it's all in parentheses, so
it's not. Yeah, yeah, I don't know. Okay, anyway, moving on. Okay,
so it says like this.
Okay, אמר ליה, amar lei, okay, so איכא דאפי... ika d'afi... where
was I? So anyway, so that is the important, so that's a
very fascinating גמרא gemara about right, minimum number of kids per class
and
about which are the preferred teachers and I appreciate the correction that
the idea is, first of all, that you can fire a teacher
and that that'll get everybody to work harder. And second of all,
that it's not the quantity but it's making sure that they get
it correctly and being on top of the kid for the follow
up. So now the גמרא gemara says like this, according to one
view, but it seems to be the one the גמרא's gemara's ending
with. Now, ואמר רבא, v'amar rava, מקרי
ינוקא, makrei yenuka, שתלא, shatla, טבחא, tavcha, ואומנא, v'umana, וסופר מתא, v'sofer
mata, כולן כמותרין ועומדין דמינהו. kulan kemutarim v'omdim deminhu. So all these
following people, if you give a person a job review, you're supposed
to say well, you've got these problems or whatever, if you don't
improve them, we might have to let you go. So Rava says
you don't have to give any warning to the following people because
what they're doing is
so important and also it's a, as we're going to say, it's
a type of a loss that can't be recovered if they do
it incorrectly, that they can be fired on the spot without warning.
That's what מותרין ועומדין mutarim v'omdin means. Okay, who can be fired
on the spot without warning for doing a bad job?
So, I'm sorry, what was it? So מקרי ינוקא, makrei yenuka, a
schoolteacher, because as we've seen, you make a mistake and it's hard
to get the mistake out. שתלא shatla is a sharecropper. So that's
the harder one to understand, so he does a bad job in
sharecropping, so maybe he can compensate. What do you mean that it
can't
be a loss that can't be made up? But anyway, we'll get
back to that. טבחא tavcha is a butcher. He slaughters the animal
and obviously if he slaughters it incorrectly it's a נבילה. nevila. ואומנא
v'umana is a bloodletter, obviously somebody
can die as a result, certainly not be healed. וסופר מתא, v'sofer
mata, so תוספות tosafot says this is a scribe, because if you
write a bad document and you were supposed to
receive $1,000 and you wrote
$100, what are you going to do?
That you can't recover that loss. So all of those things are
irrecoverable losses.
כל פסידא דלא הדר, kol psida d'lo hadar, any irrecoverable loss, מותרין
ועומדין. mutarim v'omdin. So that person who works in that profession is
considered to be pre-warned and can be fired on the spot. אמר
רב הונא, amar rav huna, האי בר מבוא דאוקי ריחיא. hai bar
mavoi d'oki reicheia. Now we're moving back away from the school children
and back to more general discussions. מוזהר ועומד לשון התראה. muzhar v'omed
lashon hatra'ah. Yeah. Okay, so אמר רב הונא, amar rav huna, האי
בר מבוא דאוקי ריחיא, hai bar mavoi d'oki reicheia, ואתא בר
מבוא חבריה וקא מוקי גביה. v'ata bar mavoi chavreih v'ka moki gaveih.
So a person in a מבוי, mavoi, now מבוי mavoi is bigger
than a חצר, chatzer, right? A מבוי mavoi is this thing that
has multiple חצרות chatzerot opening up into it. So before we were
saying what can you restrict go on in your חצר? chatzer? We
pointed out if you can't be upset if there's a school opening
up in the next חצר, chatzer, you don't have a right to
complain, it's only in your חצר. chatzer. Now we're going to talk
about what if something's happening in the whole
מבוי, mavoi, what can you complain about? So let's take a look.
So this is obviously something that would be possibly even more disruptive.
So האי בר מבוא דאוקי ריחיא, hai bar mavoi d'oki reicheia, so
you're putting in a
mill. ואתא בר מבוא חבריה וקא מוקי גביה, v'ata bar mavoi chavreih
v'ka moki gaveih, and now the issue here is not the issue
of noise, noise and foot traffic whatever, that's only in your חצר.
chatzer. Here we're actually shifting gears to a very important concept which
is the concept that you might have heard of of הסגת גבול,
hasagat gvul, although that's not a phrase that the גמרא gemara is
using, which is competing with my business. I was here first, I
was doing the business for the whole מבוי, mavoi, for this whole
neighborhood, and you're opening up a competing enterprise. Do I have a
right to say you can't compete with my enterprise, I was here
first? And that's why we're dealing with a bigger space, a מבוי.
mavoi. Alright? Even in a larger sort of neighborhood, if I was
here first, maybe you can't compete. So האי בר מבוא דאוקי ריחיא,
hai bar mavoi d'oki reicheia, ואתא בר מבוא חבריה וקא מוקי גביה,
v'ata bar mavoi chavreih v'ka moki gaveih, another person from the מבוי
mavoi comes and has another one next to him. גביה gaveih presumably
means anywhere in the courtyard.
דינא הוא דמעכב עילויה, dina hu d'me'akev ileih, the other guy can
say, "Hey, you can't do that, I was here first. אמר ליה,
amar lei, קפסקת ליה לחיותי. ka pasket lei l'chayuti. You have basically
encroached on my living, on my livelihood." So לימא מסייע ליה. lima
mesayei lei. Let's see if we can support this. מרחיקין מצודת הדג
מן הדג כמלוא ריצת הדג. marchikin metzudas hadog min hadog kemaloi ritzas
hadog.
So I basically, the way רש"י Rashi explains it, is I've been
basically hunting a particular fish, or you know, and or I see
that there's a place where the fish are gathering, I've been scoped
out a place, I've been throwing food in a particular area there,
and I am like having my net there. That's the place that
I've been scoping out and I've been working on. You have to
stay away from that since I was there first, the amount of
distance of ריצת הדג. ritzas hadog. I don't know exactly what, the
flight of a fish, whatever that means. ואמר v'ama רבה בר רב
הונא Rabbah bar Rav Huna עד פרסה. ad parsa. א פרסה parsa
which is 2000 אמה, ama, which is like a, which is like
a kilometer. What? It goes four mil. Oh, 8000, right. א פרסה,
parsa, oh right, א פרסה parsa is four מיל, mil, 8000 אמה.
ama. 2.4 seven point nine. Right. So how much is that? 2.4.
Wow, so two and a half miles. Okay, so that's a lot.
Okay, so somebody scopes out a place and everybody has to stay
away two and a half miles.
So I guess it means that if that is actually the reality,
עד פרסה. ad parsa. Okay. Anyway, so you see that basically somebody
is there first, you have to stay away. So this is
no, שאני דגים דיהבי סיירא. shani dagim d'yahavi siyara. No, fish are
different because basically you have, רש"י Rashi says, you know, they they
are focused on a particular location. If you've been putting food in
a particular space then they're all sort of gathering there and they
know that that's the place where there is food. So you've already,
now what does that mean? So okay, that just means you've been
there first. But רש"י Rashi says, no, that's a little different. That's
like you've already sort of had been working on capturing the fish.
It's a particular fish and you almost almost have your, you know,
you have like your claim on that stick, on that fish, on
those fish. Whereas if you open up a competing business, it's not
like you have your claim on these customers. Customers can come from
anywhere. Right? It's not like a very specific like type of a
fish that it's like you already have it in your hand. That's
if you look at רש"י, Rashi, the way רש"י Rashi describes the
difference. He says the following, he says, בטוח הוא שיקדנו, batuach hu
sheyekadnu,
in this case you're confident that you'll capture it, הוי ליה כמאן
דמטא לידיה, havay lay keman d'mata l'yaday, it's like you already have
it in your hand, ואידך חבריה מזיק ליה, v'idach chavray mazik lay,
and it's like the other person is sort of damaging, taking away
from you. אבל הכא מי שבא אצלי יבוא, מי שבא אצלך יבוא.
aval hacha mi sheba etzli yavo, mi sheba etzlecha yavo.
But here it's like, you know, you'll get your customers, I'll get
my customers, it's not like you have a claim on every every
every potential future customer. All right, so so anyway, it's not exactly
clear what the lines are between those two, but anyway some see
it as something very concrete. It's not about a customer base, it's
about a thing that I'm trying to possess and it's like I'm
already in the process of possessing it, and that makes it a
little bit different. It's not about competing for customers. So אמר ליה
רבינא לרבא. amar lay Ravina l'Rava. So רבינא Ravina said to רבא,
Rava, לימא רב הונא דאמר כרבי יהודה? leima Rav Huna d'amar k'Rabbi
Yehuda? Maybe רב הונא Rav Huna who says you can't open up
a competing business says like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? דתנן, detnan, we
learned in a משנה, mishna, רבי יהודה אומר לא יחלק חנווני קליות
ואגוזים לתינוקות מפני שמרגילן אצלו, Rabbi Yehuda omer lo yachalek chanvani kliyos
ve'egozim letinokos mipnei shemargilan etzlo,
that you basically, there are already two stores and you are going
to give out free candy in your stores, and that's why all
the kids whose parents sent them to buy something in the store
are going to come to your store. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says you're not allowed to, that's unfair competition. וחכמים מתירים, vachachamim matirin,
and the חכמים chachamim say why is it unfair competition? אף הוא
עושה בקליות, af hu oseh bekliyos, because, you know, he can also
give out, you know, of candy. Okay, so you see in this
is an issue, right? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't want you to
engage in unfair competition, so maybe it's the same idea that you
can't open up a competing store. So obviously there's a difference here.
There there are already two stores, you have a right to be
doing your business, and the question is what's considered fair business practices?
That's different from a question about whether you can be, you know,
you know, are not allowed to open up your store. So that's
what the גמרא Gemara says. The גמרא Gemara says, אפילו תימא רבנן.
afilu teima Rabbanan. No, no, even the חכמים Rabbanan there that that
allow you, in theory could go like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, or
could go like the idea that you can't open up a competing
business. עד כאן לא פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי יהודה התם אלא דאמר
ליה אנא מפלגינא אמגוזי ואת פלגי כוסטא, ad kan lo pligi Rabbanan
alei d'Rabbi Yehuda hasam ela d'amar lay ana mapalgina amgozai v'at palgi
kusta, whatever.
I'm distributing this type of nuts, you distribute another type of nuts.
Meaning there the debate is that it's not unfair competition because you
can do the same thing I'm doing. So that's what that debate
is.
אבל הכא אפילו רבנן מודו, aval hacha afilu Rabbanan modu, but here
maybe even the rabbis would agree that you're not allowed to open
up a competing business, דאמר ליה קא פסקת ליה לחיותי, d'amar lay
ka paskat lay l'chayusi, you are basically encroaching on my livelihood. So
you could go both ways I think. The גמרא Gemara only goes
one way, right? You could say here you could sort of say
you're allowed to give out candy because the other guy give out
candy, but we could all agree that somebody who doesn't have a
business yet can't come in here and open up a business and
compete with mine. Right? You could say the opposite, you could say,
you know, that that's very protectionist, right? Everybody, you know, the more
businesses that are open, the better the consumer's off, you know, more
free market competition etc. You know, you have to make a business,
fine, but why should I be prevented from making a business too
just because you opened your store, you know, a week before me?
Right? So maybe everybody has a right to open up a business,
but once we have businesses we can't engage in. In unfair practices
of competition. So I sort of see the ability to
distinguish them in both directions, right, what's considered to be fair competition,
and the other is to what degree can you restrain somebody from
opening up a business? But the גמרא Gemara sort of sees at
least following רב הונא's Rav Huna initial position that the person you
have to protect more is the one that's already got the business
there whose business is now being threatened. And maybe that person deserves
some more protection than if you have two existing businesses and there's
a question about what type of practice they're engaging in. So we're
going to continue with this important discussion tomorrow about is there this
idea of not opening up a competing type of an enter... of
a business or not. Rabbi? Yes.